In this segment we're going to look at our first key exchange protocol without a trusted third party.
在这一节中我们来看一下在没有
可信第三方的情况下的第一密钥交换协议
So the settings are, we have our friends Alice and Bob as usual.
我们像往常一样设两个朋友Alice和Bob
And these friends have never met before but somehow they want to generate a shared key.
并且这两人之前并没有见过，但他们都想产生一个共享密钥
So what they're going to do is they're going to send messages to one another, back and forth.
他们将来回地互相发送信息
And this time there is no trusted third party that they can communicate with.
并且这次他们的通信是没有可信第三方的
And at the end of this protocol, somehow they should have a shared key that they both know.
在协议的最后，他们应该有两人都知道的共享密钥
So there's a secret key k that they both know.
所以会有一个他们都知道的密钥k
But an eavesdropper who listens in on this traffic has absolutely no idea what this secret key k is.
但是窃听者监听这条通道时完全不知道密钥k是什么
For now we're just going to worry about attackers that only eavesdrop on the conversation.
现在当我们只要担心窃听对话的攻击者
In other words, we don't allow any tampering with traffic.
换句话说，我们不允许对通道的任何篡改
All we allow is just eavesdropping, and yet eavesdroppers should
我们所允许的只是监听，而且监听者
have no idea what the secret key k is.
并不知道密钥k
So we're going to look at a number of key exchange protocols in these settings.
在这些设定下，我们将看到许多密钥交换协议
Namely, when the attacker is only eavesdropping on the conversation
很明显，当攻击者只窃听会话
but cannot change traffic. And we're going to see three protocols that achieve this goal.
但不能改变通信量。并且我们将要看到实现这一目标的三个协议
And the first question, though, for this segment, is
这节第一个问题是
"Can this be done only using symmetric crypto?"
“只是用对称密码学能做到吗？”
So can this only be done using block ciphers or hash functions, or any of the tools
可以只是用分组加密或者哈希函数，或者
that we've seen in the last four weeks.
任何我们在过去4周学过的工具来实现吗
And so very surprisingly, the answer is "Yes", in fact we can do key exchange
令人惊奇的是，答案是肯定的。事实上，我们可以做密钥交换
just using block ciphers or hash functions without a trusted third party
仅仅使用分组加密或者哈希函数，不借助可信第三方
but unfortunately the resulting protocols are very inefficient and are actually never used in practice.
但不幸的是，结果协议非常无效，事实上从没有应用到实践中
Nevertheless, these are very simple protocols and so I want to show you how they work,
尽管如此，存在一个简单的协议，我会告诉你它们如何工作
and then we'll move on to the more efficient protocols that we'll discuss this week and the next.
并且他们会转为更加有效的协议，我们将在这周和下周讨论
So the simple protocol I want to show you what's called a Merkle Puzzles protocol.
我想告诉你的这个简单协议叫Merkle谜题协议
This protocol was invented by Ralph Merkle back in 1974 when he was just an undergraduate.
这个协议是由Ralph Merkle在1974年发明的，当时他还是个大学生
Interestingly, he invented this protocol as part of a seminar that he took,
有趣的是，他发明这个协议是作为他参加的小组研讨的一部分
but apparently the professor didn't quite understand the significance of the contribution
但是显然，教授没有很好地理解这个结构的意义
and as a result Ralph Merkle actually graduated and then moved
最后Ralph Merkle毕业，又来到斯坦福大学
to Stanford where he became Marty Hellman's student
在那里他成了Marty Hellman的学生
and they've done a lot of good things in public-key cryptography since then.
自从那时起他们做了许多有关公共密钥密码术的研究
So let me show you how Merkle Puzzles work.
接下来让我给大家展示Merkle Puzzles是怎么工作的
The main tool for this protocol is what's called a "puzzle"
这个协议的主要工具叫做一个“谜题”
and let me explain what I mean by a puzzle.
让我解释一下“谜题”的意思
A puzzle is a problem that's difficult to solve, but can be solved with some effort.
一个谜题就是一个很难解决的问题，但可以通过一些努力去解决
In other words, if you really put your mind to it you can solve it.
换句话说，如果你真的想着这个问题那么你就可以解决它
So let me give an example.
那么让我举个例子
Suppose we have a symmetric cipher that uses keys that are 128 bits long
假设我们有一个对称密码，它使用128位长的密钥
So just think of AES for example.
可以想到AES例子
And suppose what I do is a choose an AES key such that the first 96 bits are all 0
假设我选择一个前96位都为零的AES密钥
and only the remaining 32 bits are non-zero and just chosen at random.
只有剩下的32位非零，并且随机选择
Ok, so only 32 bits of this 128-bit key are random. The rest are all 0.
好，那么只有这个128位密钥的32位是随机的。剩下的都为零
And now what I do is I encrypt a fixed plaintext, for example,
我要做的是加密一个固定的明文，
simply the plaintext "message" using this 128-bit key that happens to be mostly 0.
这个明文“message”使用的是大部分为零的128为密钥
The result is what I would call a "puzzle".
结果叫就叫做“谜题”
The reason I call it a puzzle is because it's actually not that hard to find
我称之为谜题的原因是事实上并不难找到
the secret key P simply by trying all 2-to-the-32 possibilities.
密钥P，只需通过2的32次方总可能
Remember the first 96 bits are all 0, there are only 2-to-the-32 possible keys to try.
记住前96位都为零，只能尝试2的32次方种可能的密钥
And for each key we'll try to decrypt this puzzle and see if we get the plaintext "message".
并且对于每一个密钥，我们将要试着去解密这个谜题，看看是否我们得到了明文“message”
If so, we know that we've recovered the right solution, P.
如果是这样，我们就知道我们找到了正确的解决方法P
So within 2-to-the-32 work, we can actually solve this puzzle.
因此，经过这2的32次方次的工作，我们事实上可以解决谜题
Namely, we can find P just given puzzle(P).
显然，给我们谜题（p）我们就可以找到P
So the way this is going to work is as follows:
工作方法如下
Alice is going to start by generating a large number of puzzles.
Alice一开始创建了大量的谜题
In particular, she's going to generate 2-to-the-32 different puzzles.
特别地，她将建立2的32次方个不同的谜题
Now each of these puzzles, the way she generates it is as follows:
现在她建立每一个谜题的方式如下题
What' she'll do is she'll choose a 32-bit random puzzle P-i,
她选择一个32位的随机谜题P-i
(she does this for i = 1 to 2-to-the-32)
（这里i从1到2的32次方）
and then she's going to choose two more values, x-i and k-i that
之后她将选择两个值，x-i，k-i
happen to be 128-bits each.
每一个都是128位的
Now what she'll do is she'll use the puzzle P-i as an AES secret key.
她要做的是她使用谜题P-i作为AES密钥
So she'll create 128-bit key where 96 of the bits are set to 0.
因此，她讲创建一个128位的密钥，它的96位置零
And only the 32 least significant bits happen to be random.
只有32有效位是随机的
So this is a key that only has 32bits of entropy, if you like,
所以这个密钥的墒是3位的
and there are only 2-to-the-32 such keys.
并且只有2的32次方个这样的密钥
Now the plaintext that she'll encrypt using this key
现在她用这个密钥加密的明文
is this message that I wrote over here.
我把它写在这
Basically it's starts off with the word "Puzzle".
基本上，它以“puzzle”开头
That puzzle is identified by the identifier x-i,
谜题被定义成x-i
which happens to be 128 bits.
正好是128位
And to that we concatenate a value k-i which also happens
我们在x-i后面附上k-i，k-i也刚好
to be 128 bits.
是128位
So she does this for all 2-to-the-32 puzzles, and as a result
所以她对所有2的32次方个谜题，因此
she gets 2-to-the-32 different puzzles.
她得到了2的32次方个不同的谜题
She then goes ahead and sends these 2-to-the-32 puzzles to Bob.
她继续将这些2的32次方个谜题发给Bob
So what does Bob do?
那么Bob会怎么做呢？
Well Bob receives this flood of 2-to-the-32 different puzzles.
Bob接收2的32次方个不同的谜题
He's just going to choose one of them.
他只选择其中的一个
He doesn't even have to remember any of them.
他甚至不必记住任何一个
He just randomly lets most of them go by.
他只要随机的忽略大部分的谜题
And he happens to choose one of them.
然后只选择其中的一个
Let's say he chose puzzle number "j".
假设他选择了谜题“j”
Then he spends time 2-to-the-32 and solves this puzzle.
然后他花2的32次方的时间去解这个谜题
Well what does it mean to solve this puzzle?
解决谜题是什么意思呢
He's going to try all possible values of P-i.
他将会尝试p-i所有可能的值
He's going to decrypt the puzzle that he chose, and
他将解密他选择的这一谜题
he's going to check whether the first part of the plaintext starts
并且他会检查是否明文的首部
with the word puzzle.
以puzzle开头
And if it does, he knows that he's correctly solved that puzzle,
如果是这样，他就会知道他正确地解了这个谜题
and he basically obtains the data embedded in the puzzle
并且基本上获得了谜题中嵌入的数据
namely, x-j and k-j.
x-j，k-j
Remember x-j is this value that identifies the puzzle
记住，x-j定义了谜题
and k-j is going to be a secret that they use.
而k-j是他是他使用的一个密钥
So now he's solved the puzzle -- he knows that he's solved the puzzle correctly
现在他解决了谜题--他知道他正确地解决了谜题
and he obtained this x-j and k-j.
并且得到了x-j和k-j
What he'll do is he'll send x-j back to Alice
他接下来要做的是将x-j传回给Alice
-- just the value of x-j. k-j he keeps for himself, and keeps it a secret.
--只是x-j的值。k-j他自己保留，而且将它保密
And then Alice is simply going to lookup in her database
然后Alice在她的谜题数据库中查找
of puzzles, she's going to lookup puzzle number x-j,
她将要去查找谜题x-j
and then she knows Bob chose the key k-j.
之后她就知道了Bob选择了密钥k-j
And now they have this shared key.
现在他们拥有了这个共享密钥
So k-j is going to be the shared key they that use to communicate securely with one another.
因此k-j就成为了他们用来互相安全交流的共享密钥
So in a diagram the way this protocol works is as follows:
所以在示意图中这个协议工作的方式如下
Alice starts off by sending 2-to-the-32 puzzles to Bob.
Alice开始向Bob传了2的32次方的谜题
So we can generalize this. Let's say that she says n puzzles to Bob.
我们可以推广这一说法。她想Bob发送了n个谜题
And lets say that each puzzle takes work proportional to n to solve.
每个谜题需要花费正比于n的时间去解决
Bob solves one of these puzzles,
Bob解出了其中一个谜题
and then he sends back x-j to Alice.
并且他将x-j回送给Alice
So far each one of them has spent work n.
目前双方都花了时间n
And then Alice basically looks up puzzle x-j
然后Alice查看谜题x_j
and recovers the key that corresponds to this puzzle.
还原出对应于谜题的密钥
And as a result both of them now have a shared key
因此现在双方有了一个共享密钥
that they can use to communicate with one another.
他们可以使用这个密钥来相互交流
Ok so lets look at the work they did.
我们来看他们所做的工作
So the work that Alice did is that she had to prepare n puzzles.
Alice必须准备n个谜题
Well, preparing the puzzle takes constant time.
准备谜题花掉固定长的时间
She had to prepare n puzzles, so her work is roughly order n.
她必须准备n个谜题，她的工作是0（n）的
Bob chose one puzzle and solved it, so his work
Bob选择一个谜题并解决
is also proportional to order n. So linear in n.
所以他的工作是与n成正比的 与n成线性
Let's see what the eavesdropper has to do.
我们看窃听者怎么办
Well the poor eavesdropper sees these n puzzles go by
可怜的窃听者看着n个谜题过去了
and then he sees this x-j come back.
然后他看到Bob返回了一个x_j
And he doesn't really know which puzzle Bob actually solved.
攻击者并不知道Bob解的是哪个谜题
All he sees is this random value inside of the puzzle.
他看到的只是谜题中的随机值
And so to break this protocol, the eavesdropper would
为了破解这个协议，窃听者会
actually have to solve all puzzles until he finds the right puzzle
解决所有谜题，直到他找到正确的谜题
that has the value x-j in it, and then he will recover k-j.
里面有x_j,那么攻击者就会还原k_j
So my question to you is, "What is the attacker's work?"
我给大家的问题是，“攻击者要做多少工作？”
How much work did the eavesdropper have to spend
攻击者必须做多少工作
in order to break this protocol.
才能破解这个协议
So the answer is, of course, order n-squared.
答案当然是0（n^2）
You know, quadratic time in n.
n平方的时间
He had to solve n puzzles. Each puzzle takes time n to solve.
他必须解决n个谜题，每个谜题花掉时间n
And as a result he had to spend time order n-squared.
因此他必须花掉时间n^2
In our example we said that there were 2-to-the-32 puzzles
在我们的例子中，我们说过有2的32次方个谜题
and each one took 2-to-the-32 time to solve,
每个谜题需要2的32次方的时间来解决
so overall the attacker's work is roughly 2-to-the-64 steps.
所以总的来看，攻击者需要做2的64次方步工作
So you can see the problem with this protocol.
大家可以看到这个协议的问题了
First of all, the participants Alice and Bob had to do quite
首先，参与者Alice和Bob自己
a bit of work themselves.
需要做大量的工作
If you think about it, Alice basically had to send
想一想，Alice必须发送
2-to-the-32 puzzles to Bob.
2的32次方个谜题给Bob
That's many. many gigabytes that she had to send to Bob.
她必须发很多GB的数据给Bob
Like 16 or 32 gigabytes, depending on how big each puzzle is.
比如16GB或32GB，取决于谜题的大小
Bob had to spend time 2-to-the-32 to solve one of these puzzles.
Bob必须花2的32次方的时间，来解决其中的一个谜题
That would take a few seconds, too.
这大概也会花几秒钟
But then, all the security they got is that the attacker
那么他们获得的所有的安全性在于
can break this protocol in time 2-to-the-64.
攻击者可以在2的64次方的时间内破解这一协议
So 2-to-the-64 is still not considered particularly secure.
2的64次方依然不能被认为是安全的
As a result, the attacker, really, if he really wanted
因此，如果攻击者真想
to break this protocol, he could.
破解这个协议，他是可以的
So to make this secure, the participants would have to
那么为了让这个协议安全，参与双方必须
increase the parameter n.
增加参数n
And they would have to send, say, 2-to-the-64
他们必须发送，比如说，2的64次方个谜题
puzzles to one another, and then spend time 2-to-the-64
给对方，然后花2的64次方的时间
to solve each puzzle, and then the attacker's work
去解决这个谜题，那么攻击者的工作
would be 2-to-the-128, which is considered secure.
将是2的128次方，可认为是安全的了
But having the participants spend time 2-to-the-64 to
但是参与者花了2的64次方的时间
set up a secure session is a little bit too much
来建立一个安全的会话，对每个参与者来说
to ask each of these participants.
有点吃力了
So this is why this protocol is not particularly used in practice.
所以这就是为什么这个协议不实用
But nevertheless there's a really nice idea here
不过这里有一个很好的想法
in that the participants had to spend linear time,
参与者必须花线性的时间
whereas the attacker had to spend quadratic time.
而攻击者必须花平方的时间
So there's a "quadratic gap" between the amount of
这就有一个“平方鸿沟”
work that the participants had to do, versus what the attacker
横亘在参与者和攻击者的工作之间
had to do to break the protocol.
当攻击者想破解这个协议
So a natural question is, "Can we actually do better
那么一个很自然的问题是，我们能否做得更好
than a quadratic gap, just using symmetric ciphers?"
只使用对称密码，做得比平方鸿沟更好呢？
In other words, just using tools
换句话说，使用我们前面四个礼拜
that we developed in the first four weeks of the class.
在本课程中见过的技术
And the answer really is that this is unknown.
答案是未知的
We don't know whether a quadratic gap is the best that we can do.
我们不知道平方鸿沟是否是我们所能做到的最好的结果
You might even try to think about this a bit.
大家可以试着想一想
How would you use AES or SHA-256 to do key exchange
如何使用AES或SHA-256来进行密钥交换
that achieves better than a quadratic gap.
可以获得比平方鸿沟更好的结果？
But I can tell you that we believe that quadratic
不过我可以告诉大家，我们相信
is the best we can do.
平方鸿沟是我们所能做到的最好的了
And there are even some negative results along those lines.
这里还有一些负面的结果
So roughly speaking, there is a result that says
不严格地说，有一个结果说
that, in fact, if we treat the block cipher or the hash function
事实上，如果我们把分组密码或哈希函数
that we use as a black box oracle -- in other words
当做黑盒神谕来使用，换句话说
all the participants can do is just query the block cipher
参与者只能询问分组密码
or query the hash function at certain points
或询问哈希函数在特定点的值
and receive the results -- if that's all they're allowed to do,
并获得结果，如果这些是参与者所能做的全部
in other words, they're not allowed to actually use the implementation
换句话说，参与者不能实际使用
of the cipher, or the hash function, then in fact
分组密码或哈希函数的实现
there is a result that says that if the participants only query
那么事实上有一个结果告诉我们，如果参与者只能
the block cipher at n points, there will always be an attack
询问分组密码在n个点的值，那么总有一个攻击
that runs in time n-squared.
运行在n平方的时间里
So again this suggests that if all you do is use
这就是说，如果你只能使用
the block cipher as a black box that you query,
分组密码作为一个黑盒进行询问
then whatever key exchange you come up with,
那么无论交换什么密钥
there will always be a quadratic attack on this key exchange.
这个密钥交换总有一个平方时间的攻击
And, in fact, at the end of this module, I point to this
事实上，在本章结束时，我指出这篇论文
paper -- it's a fairly recent paper from 2009 -- that shows
最近的一篇2009年的论文
that quadratic is best we can do.
证明了平方是我们能做的最好的
If you want to read more about this impossibility result
如果大家想了解更多的关于这种不可能性的结果
you know, go ahead and take a look at this paper.
去读这篇文章吧
It's actually a very readable paper, and you should be able to understand it.
这篇论文可读性强，大家应该能理解它
And so the question is what to do next.
那么问题是接下来怎么办
So now we're kind of stuck.
我们有点困住了
We said that with block ciphers, we really can't do
我们说过用分组密码，我们不能
better than a quadratic gap.
做得比平方鸿沟更好
And so what do we do?
那我们怎么办
So this was kind of the starting point of public-key cryptography.
那么这就是公钥密码学的起点
And the realization is that we need more than just
我们发现，我们需要
generic block ciphers and generic hash functions.
比通用分组密码和哈希函数更多的技术
We actually need functions that have very, very special properties.
我们实际上需要具备非常特殊性质的函数
And to build these functions, we actually have to rely on some algebra.
为了构建这些函数，我们实际上必须依赖某些代数
So in the next few segments we're going to look
下面几节我们看
at some algebraic constructions and then we'll see
一些代数机制，然后我们看
how to use those for key exchange and for
如何使用它们来进行密钥交换
many other things in public-key cryptography.